All right, let's keep talking about the
1920s, y'all, and this time we're going
to focus on the enormous cultural and
demographic changes that occurred during
this saucy period. So, if you're ready
to get them brain cows milked, let's get
to it. Now, before we get to all the
spicy stuff, let me try to lay out some
1920s context for you. So, this is
Warren G. Harding caught in a candid
moment right after the photographer
asked him to use his face to express his
feelings about the progressive era.
Anyway, Harding won the presidential
election of 1920 on the promise that
under his administration, Americans
would experience a return to normalcy
after the prodigious upheavals that
occurred during World War I. And this
normalcy included deemphasizing the
idealism of progressive reforms,
returning to a posture of isolationism,
and returning to traditional
conservative values. But, as it turned
out, Americans in the 1920s experienced
enormous cultural upheaval and intense
periods of change, all of which led to
ongoing debates about what it meant to
be an American. And there were so many
factors contributing to that upheaval,
including the profound disruption caused
by World War I, the race riots of 1919,
the Red Scare, hundreds of thousands
dead by the Spanish flu. I could go on.
Oh, and by the way, if you know guys to
follow along with this video and all of
my videos, check that link in the
description. Okay, so the first big
change that occurred during the 1920s
was a massive spike in urbanization,
which, in case you forgot, describes the
growth and development of cities. So, by
1920, the federal census revealed that
more Americans lived in cities than in
rural areas, which was a big honking
demographic deal. And this shift
resulted from decades of
industrialization and wartime production
during World War I, and declining farm
profitability, improved transportation
thanks to the widespread adoption of
automobiles as the result of the
expansion of credit, etc. And so, as a
result, cities became centers of
economic opportunity and cultural
innovation and political power, while
rural areas increasingly came to
represent tradition and stability.
Additionally, this urbanization tipping
point in many ways marked the end of
that old Jeffersonian vision of an
agrarian nation filled with frolicking,
contented, and self-reliant farmers.
Anyways, American cities continued to
grow like mad. Three groups in
particular were affected by all the new
opportunities available in these urban
areas. First, urban economies created
expanded employment opportunities for
women beyond domestic labor and factory
work. So, clerical jobs such as typists
and secretaries and telephone operators
and retail workers became common,
particularly for young unmarried women.
And these positions offered regular
wages and social mobility and greater
independence from family oversight. And
I'll tell you more about some of these
women later. Okay, second, urban
economies offered new opportunities to
international immigrants as well. So, as
I mentioned in the last video,
immigration numbers went positively
bonkers during the 1920s and those
folks, much like previous waves of
immigrants, often settled in cities. And
that's because urban industrial cities
like Chicago or New York City were
bursting with factories and construction
projects and transportation industries
that relied on cheap labor. And some of
those immigrants gained significant
wealth and influence thanks to those
economic opportunities. And if you want
an example, and I know that you do, then
meet Hector Boiardi, also known as our
boy a Chef Boyardee. Yes, he was an
Italian immigrant who settled in New
York City and quickly rose to prominence
as a skilled chef. And after cooking in
several high-profile restaurants and
even for President Woodrow Wilson,
Boiardi secured partnerships with
industrial manufacturers and began mass
producing his recipes in the form of
canned goods. So, if you, like me, have
crushed some canned ravioli with a glad
heart, then let us now praise early 20th
century immigration for giving us such
saucy gems. But I should hasten to add
that this story was not the norm for
many immigrants who worked hard to
establish themselves in their new
societies, but often faced obstacles
like employment and housing
discrimination. Anyway, the third group
to benefit from the economic
opportunities in industrial cities were
internal migrants. So, internal
migration brought rural Americans,
including Southern African Americans and
white farmers from Appalachia into the
Midwest into industrial cities. In fact,
northern factories recruited these
workers aggressively during and after
World War I to replace European
immigrants after the number started
declining. And I'll tell you more about
that in a moment. Anyway, the most
significant example of this trend was
the Great Migration of over a million
black Americans out of the South and
into northern and western cities. And
since I flap my mouth hole at length
about this migration in the video for
7.6, I'll leave it there. Okay, so now
let's turn the corner and talk about the
effects of all this migration and
immigration during the 1920s. And there
are two big categories you're going to
need to know. The first effect was the
significant nativist backlash. Now,
remember that nativism refers to
policies enacted in order to protect the
interest of native-born Americans, which
most often meant white Protestant
Americans. So, nativism surged in the
aftermath of World War I because of
economic instability and labor strikes
and fear of radical political movements.
Furthermore, the Bolshevik Revolution
and the First Red Scare convinced many
Americans that immigrants, especially
those from Southern and Eastern Europe,
were carriers of contagions called
anarchism, socialism, and communism. And
so, in response, the Ku Klux Klan
experienced a significant surge in
growth during the 1920s. And while the
Klan in the 19th century primarily
focused on anti-black activities, the
rebooted 20th century Klan expanded its
acts of terror to many other groups that
represented threats to white cultural
power. Their stated goal was to work for
100% Americanism, and so they targeted
groups like Catholics and Jews and
others that they deemed immoral, like
bootleggers and gamblers. Now, probably
the most focal and hotly debated example
of 1920s nativism came in the criminal
trial of two Italian immigrants, Nicola
Sacco and Bartolomeo Vanzetti. And long
story very short, these two men were
self-professed anarchists and were
accused of committing murder during an
armed robbery. And despite their
continued professions of innocence and a
highly questionable handling of the
evidence, they were found guilty and
sentenced to death. And so, this trial
sparked a sensational nationwide debate,
since it appeared to many that these men
were being executed not based on clear
evidence, but because they were
immigrants with suspect beliefs. And
because demonstrations were held on
behalf of these men in nearly every
major US city, this event reflected a
growing social and cultural divide
concerning what it meant to be an
American. Anyway, this surge of nativism
ultimately resulted in legislative
action that aimed to reduce foreigners
in the United States. For example, in
1921, Congress passed the Emergency
Quota Act, and then in 1924, the
National Origins Act, which sharply
restricted immigration from Southern and
Eastern Europe. And then in 1924,
Congress passed the Immigration Act,
which banned immigrants from Asia
entirely. And the stated purpose of this
law was entirely informed by nativist
reasoning, namely the preservation of
the racial purity of white Americans.
And yeah, that's depressing, but the
second effect of migration definitely
hits a more positive note, namely that
internal migration led to the flowering
of significant regional ethnic art
movements. So, as a result of the Great
Migration and other internal migrations
to cities, many ethnic groups clustered
together and as a result, they found new
artistic ways to express the contours of
their unique experience. In other words,
for these marginalized people, groups,
art, and music, and literature became
tools for asserting their identity and
resisting widespread stereotypes and
redefining what it meant to be an
American. Case in point, the Harlem
Renaissance. Now, this is a black
artistic movement born in the Harlem
neighborhood of New York City and was
the direct result of the Great Migration
since a significant portion of blacks
who left the South clustered together in
New York. And being together in that
environment, the Harlem community went
absolutely nuts creating new cultural
expressions that reshaped American art
and challenged American stereotypes
against blacks. For example, Billie
Holiday was a blues and jazz singer who
used her haunting voice to challenge
racial injustice against blacks. Most
notable was her song Strange Fruit,
which directly protested Southern
lynching against black Americans. Also,
you had poets like Langston Hughes who
made use of common black diction to
express racial pride and to reject the
pressures of assimilation to white
culture. And I could very much go on,
but we've got to move right along to the
various cultural controversies that
occurred during the 20th century. Okay,
now the 1920s was a time of rapid
cultural change and experimentation. And
much like similar changes during the
Gilded Age, the rapidity of the
transition stirred up a heap of hotly
contested cultural debates as Americans
tried to make sense of it all. And gird
thyself cuz there are no less than four
categories of controversy that you're
going to need to know. First of all, you
had debates over changing gender roles.
So, after the ratification of the 19th
Amendment in 1920, which recognized
women's right to vote, American women
were now at long last political equals
to men. However, some American women
weren't satisfied with mere political
equality and began pushing for more
social equality as well. And these women
were direct heirs of the New Woman
movement during the Gilded Age, but this
revival of feminism was put on full
display by women who called themselves
flappers. And these women put their
independence on display by cutting their
hair short, smoking cigarettes in
public, No. And embracing controversial
fashion choices like knee-length skirts.
Oh yeah, needless to say all those
return-to-normalcy conservatives were
more than a little scandalized by the
sight of a woman's shin in public. And
even worse, these women flaunted all
these cultural norms without even
getting permission from a man. Can you
believe it? Anyway, the second
controversy of the age was the growing
influence of a philosophical movement
known as modernism. It was a movement
that embraced the secularization of
society and rejected traditional
societal norms as oppressive.
Additionally, because modernists had
grown skeptical of the narrative of
progress by science, they emphasized and
embraced irrationality as the chief
feature of human society, all of which
was deeply informed by the calamitous
death and destruction caused by World
War I. Anyway, one particularly famous
group of modernists was known as the
Lost Generation, which was a group of
writers that included F. Scott
Fitzgerald, Gertrude Stein, and Ernest
Hemingway, among many others. Taken
together, their works explored themes of
disillusionment that came after World
War I. You see, to them, the great
promises of scientific progress only led
to death and destruction in the war, and
therefore there was very little solid
ground on which to stand to find one's
way in the world. the third controversy
of the '20s was the debate between
religion and science about the nature of
truth. You see, since the 19th century,
many Protestant Christians felt their
own beliefs and maybe more to the point
social power and influence were under
attack from the growing acceptance of
Charles Darwin's theory of evolution. In
response, the fundamentalist movement
was born, a chief tenant of which was a
literal interpretation of the Bible. And
if the Bible was taken literally as
historic and scientific truth, then that
means according to Genesis 1, the world
and the fullness thereof was created by
God in six days and patently not the
result of billions of years of stupid
evolution. Anyway, this debate was put
on full display in the Scopes trial of
1925. Now, John Scopes was a Tennessee
teacher who deliberately challenged his
state's laws that banned the teaching of
evolution. And in the end, the trial was
less about whether Scopes broke the law,
because he obviously did, and he did so
on purpose. Rather, the performances of
celebrity lawyers like Clarence Darrow
and William Jennings Bryan transformed
the trial into a national contest
between the ideals of modernism and
fundamentalism. And ultimately, the
majority of public opinion favored the
modernist arguments, which only led
fundamentalists to double down on their
beliefs and said prove that urban values
were a threat to traditional values. And
then fourth, not surprisingly, race
issues continued to inflame controversy
during this period, especially as black
Americans sought greater opportunity for
self-expression and racial pride. Now,
one particularly extreme figure was
Marcus Garvey, who embraced black
separatism and rejected the efforts of
other black reformers who worked for
black equality and inclusion in American
society. To that end, Garvey founded the
Universal Negro Improvement Association,
which promoted black separation and
encouraged self-sufficiency through
business ownership. He also advocated a
back-to-Africa movement because he
ultimately believed that black Americans
would never achieve equality in the
United States and therefore ought to
return to their ancestral homes, which
was a position that put him at odds with
other black reformers like W.E.B. Du
Bois. Well, okay, you can click here to
watch my other videos for unit seven, or
you can click here to grab my video note
guides, which will help you get all the
contents of this course firmly grabbed
into your brain fold. Now, I'm glad you
came around and I'll catch you on the
flip-flop. I'm ler out.